Hey everyone, and thanks for jumping
back into the cryptoverse.
Today, we're going to talk about
Bitcoin, and we're going to be
discussing
the path to
a market cycle bottom for Bitcoin. If
you guys like the content, make sure you
subscribe to the channel, give the video
a thumbs up,
and I'd like to announce that we are
going to have the first ITC inaugural
conference in November
in Miami.
So, it's the ITC conference. This is the
first one, investing through the cycles,
uh
because we want to focus on on more than
just crypto, right? And and this is what
I've talked about for years, and
hopefully this conference can bring
together a lot of like-minded people who
want more rational analysis that's not
based on hype. Not to say that it's
always correct, right? Everyone gets
things wrong, but to say, "Look, we're
going to try to compile
people together who can look at these
markets in a in a rational in a non-hype
way, talk about assets that provide
value
to the world,
and not focus on
frothy stuff, okay? So,
that is the focus of the conference.
It'll be in Miami. The main conference
day is November 21st.
Uh it'll, you know, it kind of spans
that weekend, November 20th through the
22nd. There's going to be, you know,
maybe some events on on either end, um
depending on the tickets uh the the
thing on the ticket that you get, but uh
that's the time frame. So, check it out.
You can go find a link to this in the
description below or the pinned comment,
um and just scroll down, and and you can
read about it. And we're we're actually
compiling a a speak the speaker list
right now. So, uh we'll continue to work
on that. And uh those are the that's the
plan. That's the plan. I hope this is
going to be a a great conference and and
that it's the first of many. I know this
year isn't like the best year cuz price
action for for Bitcoin
really kind of sucks.
But, one of the reasons I'm doing it in
November is because I think the market
cycle bottom for Bitcoin will likely be
around that time. I could see it
occurring before November, right? Like I
mean, yes, it could occur after. I'm not
going to pretend like it can't, but
I've said many times that a a likely
market cycle low for Bitcoin could occur
in October.
So, what I want to do in this video is
just talk about a potential path
to get to a market cycle bottom. Before
we do that, I I want us to think for a
minute. Is what is happening now for
Bitcoin, is it very different than what
you see going on
in prior midterm years?
Not really. If you look at the
year-to-date ROI of Bitcoin in 2026 and
compare that to 2022 or 2018 or 2014,
you can see it's actually kind of in the
middle of these three. Like two are
lower, one is higher. But, when you take
the average, and you guys know that you
know, taking the average kind of gives
you it doesn't give you the path, it
just gives you a path to help guide
expectations, okay?
That's all it does. So, we're looking at
at
a midterm year, the current midterm
year, and looking at the average of
prior midterm years and overlaying one
standard standard deviation on top of
that average. So, what's interesting is
at this point in the cycle, Bitcoin is
normally down around 45%
from the yearly open.
We're currently only down about what?
31%
from the yearly open or so. Like you can
see it's
0.69 0.689 is where we currently are.
Normally we're at 0.554.
So, look at yearly candles and and you
can really quickly see this. If you look
at yearly candles, you can see that this
year, again, Bitcoin is down about 30%
or so from the yearly open.
On average, Bitcoin is down about 45% at
this point in the midterm years, which
would actually put Bitcoin a lot closer
to 50K and maybe even slightly below.
So, as of right now, Bitcoin is
outperforming
the average. All right?
Now, when we think about how Bitcoin
bottoms out, right? Like in what is the
path to get there? We know and we guys,
we cannot time it perfectly and this is
why I said it at the end of last year, I
said, "Look, don't even try to time the
counter trend rallies. Everything that I
do on here for the bear market counter
trend is just an academic exercise. I
haven't traded any of these rallies and
and the reason is because I've I've
tried to do it in the past and didn't
really have a lot of luck with it,
right? Like in 2022, I I timed this
rally pretty well, but then this one
I missed. Right? Like I it was a little
early on the rally and so it's so hard
to know, right? Like it is impossible to
know exactly when those counter trend
rallies can start and end. And what I
would say though is generally speaking,
you get your first drop at the end of
the post having year. That's your first
initial drop. That's when the bear
market starts, but like no one believes
it. Okay? That's where it starts. No one
believes it.
And you can see you had a big drop
that that sort of found a low at the
very beginning of the midterm year. I
mean, this was you you had another drop
earlier on. So, I guess maybe I should
point to this first one first, right?
So, you first had and I know that
doesn't look like much, but look, that
was about a 50% drop. Which when you
compare to these other ones, you can see
you also get about 50% drops on that
initial drop, maybe a little bit less,
somewhere between like 35%
That's your initial drop. You get your
first low at the end of the post-halving
year. Your second low ends up being
around February of the midterm year. You
have February 2018, February 2022. You
also have February 2014. So, February, I
don't know what it is, but Bitcoin is
allergic to the beginning of February It
just does not like the beginning of
February in midterm years.
From there, you set lower highs that are
near the bull market support band.
Sometimes it also corresponds with the
200-day moving average, right? Like if
you flip this over to the daily time
frame,
you'll see that often times these
rallies will sort of top out at that
200-day moving average in the bear
market years.
And and you can see that this time has
actually been no different.
The reason why this time feels different
to everyone is because there was no
final rotation into higher risk assets
at the end of Bitcoin's bull market.
But,
if we took our understanding
of the business cycle dynamics in 2019
and 2020 and applied that
to this top, then it all makes perfect
sense, right? So, what I'm asking you to
do is to to think about this year as a
typical midterm year.
But, the reason there was no rotation
into alts is because it's more like the
2019 top.
And we know why. Like, why do we say
it's more like the 2019 top? There was
no rotation into altcoins, number one.
Okay? So, that's that's the easiest
thing is to say, "Look, when Bitcoin
topped in June of 2019,
altcoins got annihilated after that for
several months. There was no alt season.
All right, that's one that's the first
thing.
The second thing is that in 2019, the
Fed cut three times.
Just like they cut three times in 2025.
The third thing is when you look at the
balance sheet of the Federal Reserve,
Bitcoin topped in June of 2019, two
months for quantitative tightening ended
in August. And in this cycle, Bitcoin
topped in October, two months for
quantitative tightening ended in
December.
What do you notice that happened back
then? Bitcoin bled out, just like it's
doing now, even while the balance sheet
of the Fed went up.
You see that?
So, where is Bitcoin now?
Bitcoin is in a difficult position
because realistically, in order for
Bitcoin to really start moving up, we
need looser monetary policy.
I don't necessarily believe that, and
I'll get to that in a second, but just
bear with me for a moment.
The one narrative, in order for Bitcoin
to really move up, we need looser
monetary policy.
Right?
And lower interest rates and and QE and
and and all that stuff's probably going
to come eventually, but that's what we
need.
But we're not getting that. Yeah, the
balance sheet's going up, but so what?
It did back then, too. It just wasn't
fast enough. Once they really went up,
that's where things changed. The problem
is that it didn't really go up until the
stock market started to correct. So,
then we have to think about, all right,
well, when would the stock market
correct? Because likely Bitcoin won't
have a big correction, or sorry, it
won't have a major market cycle bottom
until after the stock market corrects.
So, here's the thing about the stock
market, okay? And and this is where it
all makes sense, it all comes together,
all right?
Every midterm year since Bitcoin has
been around, there's been two main
corrections in the midterm year in
stocks.
You get your first correction at the
beginning of the year.
You see that?
2022, 2018,
2014.
10 to 20% drops.
But then, you get another correction at
the end of the midterm year.
10%, 20%,
20%.
Notice,
right? This is This is very key This is
very key here. Every time Bitcoin found
its market cycle bottom,
it occurred not in the first correction
by the stock market at the beginning of
the midterm year, but the second
correction.
You see that? So, look at this.
Bitcoin bottomed out here near the end
of 2014, early 2015, and it was at It
was after the second midterm year
correction at the end of the year. When
you look at 2018, Bitcoin bottomed out
after the second correction, kind of in
that second correction. And then last
midterm year, Bitcoin bottomed out again
in that last correction by the stock
market in the midterm year.
So,
when we talk about, you know, like, when
can Bitcoin bottom,
it all makes sense if you if you think
about it through the narrative of
monetary policy because
what would cause the Fed to potentially
pivot some on their hawkish monetary
policy stance?
Which I know they're not necessarily
saying it, but the markets just don't
believe them. When you look at market
expectations, we might be getting rate
on a rate hike
as early as September.
Maybe even sooner, but I I doubt it'll
happen in July, but who knows.
So, when you think about that,
it makes sense that there's these
headwinds for Bitcoin.
But, if there were a correction
in stocks in the second half of the
year,
some of those rate hike expectations
might go away, or maybe you would start
to see looser monetary policy get priced
in, which would probably be a tailwind
for crypto. Now, at the end of the day,
I don't really think you need a macro
narrative to support it. I mean, Bitcoin
just has been following the 4-year cycle
for for its entire existence, and I hope
that it continues to do so. But, that is
the one that you could you could say.
The other view,
and this is why
and I'll be I'll be clear about this.
Sometimes I'll provide the narrative, I
don't think you need one. And the reason
I don't think you need one is because
let's suppose
a worse outcome happens, where we do get
a lot of rate hikes.
All that means is the economy's not
falling apart, right? I mean, if they're
hiking rates, it just means the
economy's not falling apart. And if the
economy is not falling apart when
they're hiking rates, and Bitcoin
bottoms out in Q4, we're going to be
looking around and being like, "Well,
what's going on? If the economy's not
falling apart, and we're getting rate
hikes,
then maybe Bitcoin's mispriced at that
point."
So, that is my view on how this will
likely play out for Bitcoin. So, let's
talk about the path, because the path, I
mean, admittedly, it's so hard to get
right, and and you guys have seen me
through the years try to time some of
these countertrend rallies, and of
course, this time I've basically just
said, "All right, it's all an academic
exercise. I don't know exactly when the
countertrend rallies are going to occur,
but I would expect Bitcoin to find a low
in Q4.
Be that as it may, there will likely be
one
final kick, final counter trend rally
before the market cycle bottom is in.
Now, let me show you.
So, you look at 2018. You had the
February low.
You had the June low.
You had the Q4 low.
Look at 2022. You had the February low.
You had the June low.
You had the Q4 low.
14, you had the February low.
You didn't really have a June low. Um it
ended up being
an October low.
And then you also had a low in
January.
You see that?
So,
for me,
my guess,
on the way it normally plays out,
is Bitcoin stays weak.
Usually in the late June, sometimes that
weakness will persist into early July.
So, what normally happens is Bitcoin
sets a low
at the beginning of the summer.
And then we'll get a counter trend rally
kind of in the back half of the summer.
And then that'll set up the final drop
into the bottom in the fourth quarter of
the year. That is what normally happens
for Bitcoin.
The difficult thing about talking about
this stuff, and I've been talking about
it for like eight months now. The
difficult thing is that every time we
have a counter trend rally, you know,
the general consensus that I see online
is like, "Well, if you, you know, if
you're listening to Ben, then you're
waiting till October." Guys, I'm not
saying you have to wait till October to
buy. I'm just saying this is when
there's a good chance you will have a a
final low in the market. And I don't I'm
not saying it has to be October. I would
say it will be around October. If you
made me guess the month, I would guess
October, but that doesn't mean that it
has to be then, okay?
If Bitcoin were to get a big
capitulation tomorrow
and drop to like 40k or something, do
you think I'm going to sit here and and
keep screaming October?
No. I would pivot, just like any good
investor should.
But if Bitcoin continues to follow
the average of prime mid term years
then I'm just going to assume the status
quo remains unchanged. Let me show you
an example of something that would make
me pivot.
You know how if we look at the 2019
comparison, you see that big
capitulation we had thanks to the
pandemic. I'm not calling for a pandemic
crash, I want to be clear.
But
look at the look at this chart.
Compare the orange line, which is the
current bear market, to the blue one.
That's 2019 going into 2020. If you were
to get a big capitulation like that,
where you just kind of front run the
rest of the bear market
that's when you pivot, right? You don't
You don't just marry a date in time and
say, "Oh, no, it has to be now." You say
"I'm willing to pivot
if the charts allow me to."
That's my thought process here.
Okay?
So
what I think's happening is that Bitcoin
is getting squeezed here between its
bear market resistance band and the
200-week moving average.
It's what I think's happening.
And so, the path
to the market cycle bottom will likely
entail
a low
in the very beginning of the summer
a bounce
and then a final drop into Q4.
And then from that low in Q4
assuming everything else in the
macroeconomy is holding up fine
then that is where I would assume the
market cycle bottom would be.
And that is my assumption.
And so
I know it sucks right now. I know this
is like it's miserable for a lot of
people. I hope that the analysis we've
done on this channel is at least to a
small amount to a small extent helps
prepare you for this because
you know, this was always the most
likely outcome this year.
And
my hope is that by November
when we're doing this conference
things will look a little bit better.
Okay? That's my hope.
So
again, check it out. Go ahead and get
your tickets. We have the early bird
pricing right now. So make sure you guys
check that out and get the lower rate if
you want to.
And this is my first conference. So, you
know, it's not like I've done this a
thousand times before. This is my first
one. And
we're going to we're going to do the
best we can at it and I hope we can, you
know, just bring together a lot of
like-minded people to talk about these
markets and and to hear people out. You
know, like I don't want things to be an
echo chamber. I provide my opinions,
sometimes right, sometimes wrong. And
we'll try to bring another people, too,
to provide their opinions
that we think can provide a
non-hyped view of the market, more of
like a rational outlook.
And and to say, "Look, these are other
opinions." And then we take those
opinions and we we kind of compile them
in our minds together
and figure out, all right, what is what
is the most likely outcome here?
So
that is the goal of the conference. I
hope to see a lot of you guys there.
I've met a lot of people at at prior
conferences before. I've spoken a lot at
other conferences.
Uh but this one I'd like to
to just run ourselves and and and
just try to have some good discussions.
So, I hope to see a lot of you guys
there.
Uh the path to the lows for Bitcoin
I think involves a low in the early
summer, a bounce, and then a final drop
in the Q4.
I want to say one thing about altcoins,
okay? Because I know, despite my best
efforts over the last five or six years,
I know a lot of people still hold a lot
of alt coins and I've I've tried to tell
you, you know, in a lot of ways, like
look, these things are are a lot of them
are going to bleed out and go
asymptotically to zero against Bitcoin.
But,
the path for alts
is is could be quite different than for
Bitcoin, okay? So, when I talk about
this analysis, like I'm not talking
about alt coins.
As I said, I'm not talking about your
alt.
For alts, you know, it it it's a
completely different thing.
In 2018, you know, Bitcoin found a low
in June.
But, what's interesting for the altcoin
market
is that the altcoin market did not find
a low in June.
You know, I mean, it just it just bled
out, right? It did not find that low.
So,
and I'm not saying that has to happen.
Obviously, alt coins have been getting
annihilated for a long time, but
I just want to draw your attention to
that and to say, look, like if you're if
you're counting on future Bitcoin
rallies to bail you out of altcoin
positions, just recognize that that's
not necessarily the best assumption,
especially when you look at the social
interest right now in crypto and see
that it's relatively low. Like if you
look at um YouTube views of various
crypto YouTube channels, including my
own, what you'll see is that interest in
in these channels is completely dried
up. I mean, compared to where it was
several years ago. Like in 2021, these
channels were averaging around 3 to 4
million views a day.
Now, it's literally 300 Like you're
talking about an order of magnitude
less. So, if you're sitting there
wondering like why alt coins keep
bleeding, it's because people keep
leaving. That's the reason. Why do
people keep leaving? Well, there's
probably a number of reasons. Number
one, they're tired of all the of all the
garbage, right? They're tired of being
scammed by meme coins and rug pulls and
they're just tired of the grift. They
want to see
a real investment thesis. They're tired
of just all these alt coins that get
shilled by a lot of influencers that
were paid to shill them.
That's not an investment. That's just
gambling. And if you're trying to
attract investors, you're not going to
do that if the space rewards
toxic shilling of garbage. You're just
not. You know, you're going to you're
going to we're going to reap what we sow
in in that sense. So,
the industry should focus on lifting up
those that don't do that.
The industry should reward companies in
the crypto space that are actually
building something that has value and
it's not just, you know, random, you
know,
it's not just like moon stuff, like moon
boy predictions, like oh, like it's not
a circular economy. It's not any of that
stuff.
That is what the industry should reward.
If you're curious why all the developers
left crypto, it's because all the
developers that were in crypto
left because their skills were no longer
cared about. Because in the last cycle,
people mostly cared about meme coins.
So,
the phase that we're going through right
now for Bitcoin is not unfamiliar. If
you lived through the 2019 bear market
going into 2020, it's the exact same
thing in terms of no rotation in alts.
The Fed cut interest rates back then,
too.
Quantitative tightening ended.
And everything changed once we had the
crisis. So, we actually have we have we
either get the crisis that accelerates
things or we don't get the crisis and it
continues to play out like the average
of prior midterm years where we put in
slightly lower lows and slightly lower
highs.
We get our countertrend rally
uh in in the summer at some point and
and then that sets up the final low
going into the fourth quarter of the
year. That is my guess as to how this is
going to play out.
Let's see, right? Let's see if it if it
plays out like that. I hope to see a lot
of you guys at the conference. Thank you
guys for tuning in. Subscribe. Give the
video a thumbs up and I will put a link
to the conference down in the
description below and the pinned comment
if any of you guys are interested in
attending. I'll see you guys next time.
Bye.